A Guide to Robert Edwards Collection, 1800-1969
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Robert Edwards Collection 1800-1969
Thomas Balch Library
M 0129, VC 0090, BV 0015, OMB 0033
Robert Edwards Collection is a collection of books, ledgers, correspondence, writings, receipts, bills of sale, promissory notes, photographs, office judgements, and other materials relating to the families of Keene, Edwards, and Dulin.
LRobert Edwards, Virginia Beach, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Robert Edwards, Virginia Beach, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2015.0181
Historical Information
In 1829 Newton Keene (1804-1880) purchased 197 acres in what is now Sterling, VA. He established Green Plains Farm on the property, where he and his wife, Elisabeth Dulin (1806-1874), raised thirteen children. Their youngest daughter, Sarah Frances Keene (28 July 1858- 27 August 1929), later inherited the farm.
Sarah Frances Keene married Samuel Edwin Edwards (24 June 1861 - 4 August 1943), a justice of the peace and respected member of the community. "Squire Edwards", as he was known, was instrumental in developing Green Plains Farm into one of the most prosperous dairy farms in Northern Virginia and became an early member of the Maryland & Virginia Milk Producers Cooperative. Their son, Lee Edwin Edwards (23 September 1889 - 14 April 1966) married Gertrude A. Whalen (12 November 1897 - 9 October 1991) and they continued to live in the home and operate the business until the 311 acre property was sold to developers in 1961. Their nephew, Robert Erle Edwards (son of Lee's older brother Hugh Keene Edwards, 7 September 1884 -14 May 1963 and Helen Peele Edwards (8 March 1901 - 22 March 1991) donated the collection in 2015.
Scope and Content
Robert Edwards Collection is a collection of books, ledgers, correspondence, writings, receipts, bills of sale, promissory notes, photographs, office judgements, and other materials relating to the families of Keene, Edwards, and Dulin. The collection is organized by subject and then in chronological order by the first date within the document.
Arrangement
Box: folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library Edition, United States Census, United States Census and Voter Lists. http://www.ancestrylibrary.com (accessed 1 March 2017).
Ancestry Library Edition, Find A Grave Index, 1600s-Current. http://www.ancestrylibrary.com (accessed 26 May 2017).
Duncan, Patricia B. 2015. Loudoun County, Virginia Office Judgments: 1835 -1842 and 1842-1847. Heritage Books.
Edwards, Robert Erle, "A history of the Danville Military Institute" (1959). Master's Theses. Paper 148.
Findagrave.com www.findagrave.com/memorial/15839550/samuel-edwin-edwards (Accessed 10 December 2018)
Loudoun County Architectural Surveys 2003 (M 011), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
Robert Edwards Collection, 1800-1969 (M 0129), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Loudoun County, VA Cemetery Collection, 1990- (M 017), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA; Jones, Elias. 1986. Keene family history and genealogy - Microform. Salt Lake City, Utah: Filmed by the Genealogical Society of Utah. V REF 929 KEENE; Stewart, Roberta Dulin. 1984. The Dulin family in America. Ann Arbor, Mich: Braun-Brumfield. V REF 929.20973 DULIN
Contents List
- (M 0129)
  - (Box 1)
    - Farmer District Cooperative Agreement, Lee. E. Edwards, Northern VA, 1950
    - Written description of Green Plains, G.A. Edwards, 1956
    - Photocopies of newspaper articles focusing on “Lanesville”, the “Farmer’s Delight Home, “Green Plains”, an “New Town Development” in Leesburg and more, 1973-1981
    - Loudoun County Virginia Office Judgements, 1836-1869
    - Clerk of Loudoun County Court Receipts, 1837-1867
    - Documents by Newton Keene as Deputy Sherriff, 1838-1844
    - Public Notices, 1838 & 1849
    - Estray Horse Document by Newton Keene, Loudoun County Justice of the Peace, 1852
    - Chancery Court Case, Elizabeth Keene against Alfred Dulin, 1872
    - Letter to S.E. Edwards documenting warrants and checks sent, 1912, from Loudoun Justice Record book, bound volume number 7
    - Estate of John Dulin, Photocopied Pages, 1828-1829
    - Deeds related to the Keene family, 1832-1902
    - Agreement to Rent Coton Farm between Elizabeth Keene and Alfred D. Keene, 1865
    - Will of Elizabeth Keene, February 1874, Inventory of Personal Effects, February 1881. Photocopied Pages
    - Will belonging to Hardage Lane of Springhill, Montgomery County, MD, for J. Keene, Esquire, n.d.
    - Newton Keene, Bills of Sale, 1835-1849
    - Keene (Various), Bills of Sale, 1850-1859
    - Keene/Dulin Bills of Sale, 1860-1894
    - Keene et al, Promissory Notes, 1836-1895
    - Keene, Tax Bills, 1845-1899
    - Bills of Newton Keene and Charles Edwards from Dr. W.B. Day, 1850-1882
    - Account Records, 1832-1891, n.d.
    - Sherriff of Loudoun County and Fairfax County Receipts, 1833-1866 *Also see Section B. Legal Cases for actual folders
    - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1835-1888
    - Newton Keene as agent for Robert B. Richardson, 1838-1860
    - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1838-1896
    - Slave Lease Receipts and Promissory Notes, 1851-1859
    - Union Military Supplies Receipt, 1862
    - T. H. Vandevanter, Treasurer of Loudoun, payment receipts (1900), receipt (1909)
    - Receipts from T.E. Reed & Son, Undertakers and Embalmers, 1927, from large brown ledger, bound volume number 8
    - J.H. Keene receipt from tan ledger, bound volume number 5
    - Correspondence, 1857-1878
    - Wedding Invitation, Irene Stinemetz to T.C. Dulin, 1882
    - Hagerstown Almanac, 1884
    - Danville Military Academy Materials, 1894-1950
    - Hugh K. Edwards School Lesson and Attendance Letter, 1895-1896
    - Papers belonging to Samuel E. Edwards, J.P., 1910-1932
    - Photocopied newspaper clippings, Edwards and Dulin families, n.d.
    - Lee. E. Edwards’ stationary, Green Plains Dairy Farm, Sterling, VA, “For Bobby Edwards” written
    - Newton, Lane and Rogers family crests
    - Miscellaneous Paper Items, 1910-1960-n.d.
  - (Box 2)
    - Ledger with loose pages, poetry and songs, Elizabeth Dulin Keene, 1853-1864
    - Writings by H.F. Keene, “The Dying Soldier”, “Kind Words”, “General Stuart”, 1864
    - Photocopy - writings by H.F. Keene, “The Dying Soldier”, “Kind Words”, “General Stuart”, 1864
    - A. F. Keene’s letters and writings (“Spring”, “Dear Cousin”, “Envy”, “Beloved Friend” and “Friendship”), 1864
    - Photocopy - A. F. Keene’s letters and writings (“Spring”, “Dear Cousin”, “Envy”, “Beloved Friend” and “Friendship”), 1864
    - Writings and cards from Sarah Keene’s scrapbook, bound volume number 10
    - Photocopy of Harvey Lane Keene’s account of exploring the West, 1860-1865
    - Poem or lyrics, “She never blamed him – never…”, signed by Bettie D. Keene, Green Plains, Loudoun County, VA
    - ALS to Frank Keene from Annie Lee Keene with “Row your Boat” lyrics, n.d.
    - Photocopy - ALS to Frank Keene from Annie Lee Keene with “Row your Boat” lyrics, n.d.
    - “Stonewall Jackson a Sentinel”, n.d.
    - “Over the River” lyrics, n.d.
    - Photographs of Sterling School with Students identified, 1897, vc_0090_0001
    - Photographs of Danville Military Institute, 1959 vc_0090_0002
    - Photocopy of Will of Newton Keene, 1770
    - Photocopy of Deed (Book K, p448) between Richard Lee and David Boyd, Executors and John Orr, 1774
    - Deed (Book C, No. 3, p281) between Randal Latimer and Nancy Latimer his wife, and Newton Keene, 1836
    - Power of Attorney appointing William O. Slade to act as attorney for Alexander Ewell, Cordelia Ewell, Benjamin Dunn Jones and Ellen E. Ewell his wife, 1839
    - Methodist Pocket Hymn-Book, n.d., 1812, signed by A. D. Keene, with John, Alfred, Thomas, Francis, and James Dulin names written on back cover
    - Book of Martyrs; or, A History of the Lives, Sufferings, and Triumphant Deaths, of the Primitive as well as Protestant Martyrs …,1831,[inscription to S. Edwards from E.H. B[?], 1909]
    - The complete works of Shakespeare: with a memoir by Alexander Chalmers A.M., 1856, inscription “S. Edwards June 8th 1883 Atkin Hall St. Elizabeth” with other inscriptions and names appearing
    - Ledger with entries by N. Keene, includes an inscription by J. W. Keene, bond entries, and Newton Keene family genealogical entries, 1829-1851
    - Blacksmith Ledger with entries by John N. Keene and Charles Reed, 1853 and 1856
    - Justice Record (Loudoun, VA), 1852-1912
    - Justice Record (Loudoun, VA), includes fence claim template written by S.E.E., 1912–1933
    - Brown Leather Ledger, includes horse pedigrees and a genealogical entry, 1828-1837 and 1911-1913
    - Small ledger with entries by Wm. J. F. Keene, T. D. Keene and T. S. Keene, includes Civil War related notes, 1858-1872
    - Sarah F. Keene Commonplace book, includes poems and genealogical news clipping and entries, 1863-1887